Guide to the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence 1805-2024 (bulk, 1805-1982) NYHS-RG 2
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. General Correspondence, 1908-1982; 117.29 Linear feet in 282 document boxes and one oversize folder
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. E (Box 154, Folder 1)
    Receipt of photos of the Eastern Steamships Lines, Inc. ships (Acadia, J.T. Morse, and Robert E. Lee); presentation of gold medal to Wilberforce Eames for achievement in history; invoices from (manufacturers of fine writing papers) Eaton, Crane & Pike Company; collection of steamboat pictures; acknowledgements of donations; exchanges with (and payments to) the Emergency Unemployment Relief Committee and Block Community organization to assist unemployed individuals during the Depression. Subjects: George Washington, Benedict Arnold. Correspondents: Eastman Kodak Company; Wilberforce Eames; Educational Thrift Service; George S. Eddy; Electrical Survey Co.; Elwin M. Eldredge; Electric Meter Corporation.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Fa - Fi (Box 154, Folder 2)
    Includes quotes from caterers J. Fantozzi & Co.; acquisition of Four Generations of Cunninghams (Waddell Cunningham); the purchase of various volumes of Daily Times of San Francisco in 1859; exchanges of bookplates; lectures; frequent exchanges between A.J.Wall (Librarian) and historian D. Havelock Fisher. Subjects: Albert Gallatin. Correspondents: H.T.Farrar; Fairfield Historical Library; Famous Speakers, Inc. (for lectures); publisher Fascimile Text Society of Columbia University; Federation Settlement; Hamilton Fish, Jr.; John C. Fitzpatrick (lecturer on George Washington); Fisk University Library; and The Fifth Avenue Bank of New York.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Fairchild, Charles S. (Mrs.) (Box 154, Folder 3)
    Includes exchanges with Mrs. Charles S. Fairchild in regard to the loan of several pieces of silver; Van der Kemp letters to Governor De Witt Clinton; telegrams announcing her death (May 1931). Subjects: Grover Cleveland and Governor Seymour.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Field Exploration Committee, 1916-1932 (Box 154, Folder 4)
    Primarily includes exchanges between A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and William L. Calver; translation of letter from German into English in regard to Hessian regiments during the Revolution; Calver's schedule with the Committee; reports. Subjects: Early military buttons in America and anniversary of first inauguration.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Fl - Fo (Box 154, Folder 5)
    Subjects: Hell Gate and Grover Cleveland. Correspondents: George Allston Flagg; United States Dept. of the Interior Yorktown, VA; Florida Archaeological Society; Hugh M. Flick.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Foreign (except Great Britain) (Box 154, Folder 6)
    Mainly consists of letters written in German which A.J.Wall (N-YHS librarian) translated in regard to appraisal requests; referrals to outside institutions; requests for prints of New York streets from 1830-1840; also includes correspondence written in French from various French institutions. Subjects: Egyptian Old Kingdom reliefs. Correspondents: Deutsche Bank und Disconto-Gesellschaft; Der Propylaen-Verlag; Spanish-American Club; Consulate General of the Netherlands; Fondation Egyptologique Reine Elisabeth; Egypt Exploration Society.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Fr - Fu (Box 154, Folder 7)
    Includes series of letters in regard to the building of a public swimming pool adjoining the Friends Meeting House in Flushing, NY, and efforts by the First Congregational Church to oppose the construction (license to construct the pool was denied by the City of New York); series of letters exchanged between A.J.Wall (Librarian) and Librarian Ethelwyn Manning (Frick Art Reference Library). Subjects: Beekman portraits, Pierrepont's portrait of Washington by Gilbert Stuart, George Washington's role in Yonkers during Revolutionary War. Correspondents: Genealogist Josephine C. Frost; Industrial Machine Co.; Society of Friends; International Benjamin Franklin Society.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Ga - Gi (Box 154, Folder 8)
    Majority of correspondence concerns R. Horace Gallatin and the Gallatin papers: the re-election of R. Horace Gallatin as Third Vice-President of the Society; several letters pertain to granting permission from Gallatin family for researchers to examine portions of the Gallatin Papers and Voltaire Papers contained within; resolution making St. Ann's Church graveyard a National Shrine to Mrs. Gallatin; also includes lectures; and exchanges with the Georgia Historical Society. Subjects: Aaron Burr, George Washington portrait by Peale, and the New York Custom House. Correspondents: Gane Brothers & Co. of New York (bookbinders' supplies); New York University; General Education Board; Georgia Historical Society Library; The Genealogical Guild; publishers Ginn and Company; Harrold E. Gillingham.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Gl - Gy (Box 155, Folder 1)
    Includes series of letters between A.J. Wall (Librarian) and Director of the Department of Education (Colonial Williamsburg) T.R. Goodwin in regard to historical documents, illustrations, and photographs for the restoration of Colonial Williamsburg; Goodwin engaged the architecture firm of Perry, Shaw and Hepburn; presentation of gold medal to Wilberforce Eames. Subjects: William Cullen Bryant; Yorktown Sesquicentennial Association. Correspondents: Charles I. Glicksberg; Goodspeed's Book Shop.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Haa - Hal (Box 155, Folder 2)
    Includes series of letters from the Westchester County Historical Society in regard to George Washington's time in White Plains during the Revolution. Subjects: General Marquis de Lafayette, bookplates in Landauer collection, George Washington, Purdy-Ferris house, "Teatown." Correspondents: Richard T.H. Halsey; G.J.Hall Bookseller; Westchester County Historical Society.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Ham - Haz (2 folders) (Box 155, Folder 3-4)
    Includes the election of Cardinal Hayes as associate member of Society; series of letters between A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and Alfred C. Potter (Harvard College Librarian) with regard to a book purchased by N-YHS from Schulte's Book store, Set of Plans and Forts in America Reduced from Actual Surveys, which had been stolen from Harvard Library; lecture programs. Subjects: Oakes Smith collection, Ignaz Anton Pilat, Governor Henry Hamilton, Washington Bicentennial Commission, Gulian C. Verplanck, Alexander Hamilton, mortgage policies. Correspondents: Cardinal Hayes; Germanic Museum (Harvard); Harvard University; Hamburg-American Line; (map engravers, printers, and publishers) C.S.Hammon & Company; historian Alvin F. Harlow; State Library and Museum (Pennsylvania); New York Life Insurance Co.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. He (Box 155, Folder 5)
    Includes referrals to outside institutions; invoice for cardboard order from (vendor) C.B.Hewitt & Brothers; majority of letters are between A.J.Wall and Erskine Hewitt, Esq.; also includes acknowledgement of the presentation of a copy of the "History of the Organization and Work of the National Society, Daughters of the Revolution." Subjects: George Washington Bicentennial celebration. Correspondents: Hendrix College.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Heartman, Charles F. (Box 155, Folder 6)
    Correspondence between A.J. Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and bookseller/auctioneer Charles F. Heartman discussing the purchase of Supreme Court minutes, diaries, Rodney Letter Books, Mills and Hicks Register for 1775, newspapers, and gazettes.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Hi - Ho (Box 156, Folder 1)
    Includes solicitations to Society to purchase items of historic value; publications and leaflets sent from outside institutions, such as the The Hispanic Society of America; several letters in regard to lectures. Subjects: Hinckley Family, George Washington, Governor DeWitt Clinton. Correspondents: Gallery of P. Jackson Higgs; Historical Publication Society; Holland American Line; Honeywood Press (publishers of historical data relating to northeastern New York); Howard University; Hoffmann Machinery & Engraving Co.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Hoffman, Samuel Verplanck (Box 156, Folder 2)
    Consists of letters from A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) to Samuel V. Hoffman informing him of the outstanding bills for books (French and Indian and Van Cleve diaries) ordered from several publishers: The Baker & Taylor Co., Charles Heartman, Cadmus Book Shop, Dauber & Pine Bookshops.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Hotchkiss, Thomas W. (re Bella Landauer) (Box 156, Folder 3)
    Consists of exchanges between editor Hotchkiss and A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) in regard to Hotchkiss arranging, cataloging, and filing trade and business cards in the Bella Landauer collection over several months at the N-YHS. The letters reflect the time and expenses spent, in particular, the issue of Hotchkiss insisiting that he had not been compensated for some of the work he did.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Hu - Hy (Box 156, Folder 4)
    Includes exchanges between the Hudson River Day Line and N-YHS in regard to the disposition of old paintings of steamboats. Subjects: Robert F. Livingston and DeWitt Clinton. Correspondents: Paris Chancery Portrait Committee; James H. Hyde; Charles Bulkley Hubbell.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Huntington (Box 156, Folder 5)
    Bulk consists of exchanges between A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and librarian Leslie M. Bliss, including N-YHS proceedings, photostat requests, copies of books, acknowledgement of receipt of the Church Americana Catalogue from the Huntington Library; genealogical queries; also includes correspondence between A.J.Wall and Archer Huntington with regard to John Knickerbacker, Jr. Subjects: Horatio Seymour.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. IB - IT (Box 156, Folder 6)
    Includes acknowledgements of acquisitions to N-YHS and fire insurance invoices for N-YHS. Subject: Edwin Forbes. Correspondents: Hannah Collins Isham; Frederick B. Thomason Insurance; Institute of American Genealogy; Illinois State Historical Library.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Ives, C.W. (Box 156, Folder 7)
    Consists of exchanges between A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and C.W.Ives in regard to N-YHS's interest in securing volumes of newspapers before 1875; various items for sale as offered by Ives and receipts for payment for items sold to Society.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. J (Box 156, Folder 8)
    Includes memos to Peter A. Juley (photographer) for requests for negatives and prints from the collections; requests to purchase items to add to the Society's collections; receipts for payment to Library of Congress Division of Manuscripts for fee for maintaining the annual bibliography, Writings on American History. Subjects: Alexander Hamilton, Aaron Burr, Marquis de Lafayette. Correspondents: Long Island University; C.K.Johnson; Milbank Johnson; Institute of Jamaica.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Jaffe, Arthur (Box 156, Folder 9)
    Consists of letters exchanged between A.J. Wall (N-YHS Librarian) and Jaffe (Metropolitan Museum of Art) in regard to photos taken of the Jefferson bust to be sent to Max Farrand of the Huntington Library; other requests such as photo reproductions.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Ka - Ki (Box 157, Folder 1)
    Includes acknowledgements of presentations of items to the Society; the wills of Robert R. Randall and Thomas Randall; thank you note from a young student; estimates for repairs, cleanings, and painting in N-YHS from (Builders-engineers) William V. Kiehnle. Correspondents: Edwin P. Kilroe; Charles H. Kip.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Kl - Ky (Box 157, Folder 2)
    Includes presentation to N-YHS of painting of old volunteer fire engine No. 21 by artist William Drew (foreman) in 1846 from W.G. Kurau. Subjects: Grant's Tomb.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. La - Le (Box 157, Folder 3)
    Includes bookplates forwarded to the library by Bella Landauer; donations to the Society; lectures. Correspondents: Lewis Historical Publishing Company and The Pennsylvania Railroad.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Landauer, Bella C. (Box 157, Folder 4)
    Discusses the Landauer bookplate collection, Smith plates and costs associated with the Smith collection; preparations for the bookplate exhibition, receipt of Landauer's books, Chalking the Hat and Some Early Vermont Invitations; several postcards sent to the N-YHS library. Several letters discuss the trade card collection and finding someone to arrange that collection.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Lh - Li (Box 157, Folder 5)
    Includes estimates for museum cases; exchanges between A.J. Wall and the Library of Congress Chief of Division of Maps and Division of Accessions with regard to annual reports, copies of materials, and photostat requests. Subjects: Greenwood Cemetery, Bicentennial Celebration, Samuel Latham Mitchell Barlow, and Mount Vernon. Correspondents: J.J.Little & Ives Co., The Abraham Lincoln Association, Hobbies Magazine, Library Company of Philadelphia.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Lo - Ly (Box 157, Folder 6)
    Includes request for use of the N-YHS auditorium for school librarians from Long Island and northern New York; acknowledgement of donations to collections; representation by member W. Gedney Beatty at the Anglo-American Conference of Historians (London); acknowledgement and thanks given to DeWitt Lockman for the purchase of an exhibition case for the Jefferson bust by Houdon. Subject: Jenny Lind, Admiral Lord Rodney. Correspondents: W.H. Lowdermilk & Company, Institute of Historical Research (University of London), House of Commons Library (London), and London Library.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Portraits by DeWitt M. Lockman, 1930-1933 (Box 157, Folder 7)
    Consists of exchanges between distinguished Americans asked to sit for portraits to be painted by DeWitt Lockman; among those on the list are the Hon. Calvin Coolidge, Cardinal Hayes, General Pershing, Franklin D. Roosevelt, John D. Rockefeller Jr., Charles Lindbergh, and Wilberforce Eames. Portraits were to be exhibited at the Society once completed. Of note are letters signed by Governor Roosevelt to make arrangements for Roosevelt to sit for the portrait prior to and following his election and inauguration as Governor (original 3 letters signed by Roosevelt are with Notable correspondence in Box 66 F 14); several exchanges discuss Calvin Coolidge sitting for his portrait (2 letters are signed by Coolidge), including a typed memo of an interview conducted by Wall and Lockman with Coolidge at the Vanderbilt Hotel.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Maa - Mal (Box 158, Folder 1)
    Includes estimate from R.H. Macy & Co. in regard to casement curtains; several requests for the proceedings of the unveiling of the portrait of Wilberforce Eames and the Society conferring him the Gold medal; acquisition of photo of Edgar Allan Poe. Subjects:Tammany Hall, Edgar Allan Poe Correspondents: Majestic Book Shop; Maryland Historical Society; Utica Conservatory of Music; Katherine E. Mairs; Thomas O. Mabbott.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Mc - Mac (Box 158, Folder 2)
    Includes requests for permission from advertising companies; acknowledgements of donations; letter from descendant of William Holmes McGuffey (wrote the first widely used series of textbooks) with regard to the purchase of McGuffey Readers; letter acknowledging the death of John E. Stillwell; requests from K. McGahan seeking work at the N-YHS during the Depression; acknowledgement of presentation to N-YHS of Aaron Burr's desk used by John E. Stillwell from 1875-1930. Subjects: Edwin Smith Papyrus Papers and Aaron Burr Correspondents include The H.K.McCann Company; Harrison A.H.McNear; McKenzie Engraving Co.; and Katherine McGahan.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. McMurtrie, Douglas C. (Box 158, Folder 3)
    Correspondence between McMurtrie, typeface designer and bibliographer of printing, and A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian), in regard to reference requests for bibliographies McMurtrie was working on. Includes N-YHS receipt of McMurtrie's books and brochures, (Early Printing in Wisconsin, and Early Printing in Milwaukee).
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Mam - Maz (Box 158, Folder 4)
    Subjects: Henry Clay, George Washington Bicentennial, flags during the American Revolution. Correspondents: Marble & Shattuck Chair Co., and Powell & Marks Insurance.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Massachusetts Historical Society (Box 158, Folder 5)
    Series of exchanges between various staff members such as Librarian Julius Tuttle, and A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian); includes step-by-step methods for silking manuscripts in use by the Massachusetts Historical Society; Subject: Americana series
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Mea - Mi (Box 158, Folder 6)
    Includes volumes of stenographic notes on "many of the debates between Lincoln and Douglas made by James B. Sheridan, secretary for Stephen A. Douglas"; order and receipts to the Medallic Art Company for gold medal presented to Wilberforce Eames. Subjects: Horatio Seymour, Stephen A. Douglas, Wilberforce Eames. Correspondents include the Michigan Historical Commission; New England Quarterly; University of Michigan; Hartford Steam Boiler Inspection & Insurance Company; The Chattanooga News.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Metropolitan Museum of Art (Box 158, Folder 7)
    Includes acknowledgements of items loaned by the Metropolitan Museum for reproduction by the N-YHS; print requests of paintings owned by the N-YHS by The Metropolitan; receipt of two volumes of Edwin Smith Surgical Papyrus by The Metropolitan. Correspondents include Alice Fenton, Ludlow Bull (curator), William Clifford (Librarian), and Herbert E. Winlock (Director).
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Mo (Box 158, Folder 8)
    Includes clipping in regard to the possibility of the removal of the sub-treasury building where Washington was inaugurated President; series of letters exchanged between Clyde Potts, Mayor of Morristown, NJ in regard to acknowledgement of the receipt of a copy of the address by Emory McClintock on Topography of Washington's Camp of 1780 and its Neighborhood, delivered before the Washington Association of NJ in 1894 and a letter to create a park to preserve Washington's encampment at Morristown, NJ (1779-1780). Subjects: Revolvers made in Patterson, NJ between 1836 and 1841, Baring Papers within Rufus King collection. Correspondents: Monmouth County Historical Association.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Morgan, John Hill (Box 158, Folder 9)
    Correspondence between art collector and scholar John Hill Morgan and A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) in regard to Morgan's article on John Ramage and receipt of galley proofs and discussions of corrections to the Ramage article (contains considerable marginalia); authenticity of a plaster cast of George Washington.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Mr - My (Box 159, Folder 1)
    Bulk consists of correspondence between William D. Murphy and A.J.Wall such as Murphy's appointment as Fourth Vice President (1930-1935) of the N-YHS following the death of John Stillwell; completing the Jefferson bust for the State of Virginia; relief funds for the support of family of late employee James F. McGahan; also includes letters to patrons in regard to sending the Edwin Smith Surgical Papyrus books. Subjects: Dunlap diaries. Correspondents: Westchester Title & Trust Company; William D. Murphy; The Museum Shop (antiques and old prints); Museum of the American Indian.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. Na - Ne (2 folders) (Box 159, Folder 2-3)
    Includes correspondence with the New York Steam Corporation in regard to the installation of a steam feeder main along 71st and Central Park West (declined due to cost); loan of a ship model made by Orlando B. Merrill for the Tercentenary (tricentennial) celebration of Massachusetts; letter describing the founding and history of the Naval History Society prior to being turned over to the N-YHS in 1925; arrangement for a group of children to visit the Society. Subjects: Robert E. Lee. Correspondents: New Jersey State Library; New York Academy of Sciences; Waddy B. Wood; National Geographic Society.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New Hampshire - New York City (Box 159, Folder 4)
    Acquisition of duplicates of newspapers (New Hampshire Gazette, Portsmouth, Signs of the Times, Portsmouth); newly elected Society member Otis Hammond (Librarian of the New Hampshire Historical Society); several letters discuss the proposal for new building for the New Jersey Historical Society and whether to secure a resident janitor; the unveiling of a monument in memory of Gouverneur Morris in St. Ann's Church; N-YHS utilities; employer's pay roll summary listing positions; real estate document of tax exempt status of Society; certificate of electrical inspection; electric wiring certificate from New York Board of Fire Underwriters. Correspondents: New Hampshire Historical Society; French Church du Saint-Esprit; Edward Charles Russell (Rector of St. Ann's Church); City of New York.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New York City. Colleges and Schools (Box 159, Folder 5)
    Includes request by New York University to N-YHS to distribute circulars announcing special courses; receipts for books sent to New York Training School for Teachers; invitation for A.J.Wall (N-YHS Librarian) to attend a meeting of teachers to present "the opportunities for service which (N-YHS) offers," held at the American Museum of Natural History; several letters from the Civics department at Washington Irving High School discuss the publication of a historical guidebook on places Washington was associated with in preparation for the Washington Bicentennial (requested materials on Washington); letters to various schools in regard to a set of 94 half tone reproductions of portraits, early views, and relics owned by the Society. Subjects: New York University, Washington Irving High School, The College of the City of New York, Public School 78.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New York City. Newspapers, 1929-1932 (Box 159, Folder 6)
    Exchanges with newspapers (New York Times, New York Times Index, The World, New York Evening Post, New York American, The Sun, Current History Magazine, New York World-Telegram) with regard to subscription services, upcoming lectures, reference requests, publicity for exhibitions, general museum publicity; includes the provenance of the Edwin Smith Surgical Papers as described in a letter sent to the Evening Post. Subjects: chair Washington used to sign the death warrant of Major John Andre and Field Exploration Committee.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New York Edison - New York Genealogical, 1929-1932 (Box 159, Folder 7)
    Consists of letters exchanged between the New York Edison Gas Company discuss the kilowatt consumption of the museum and discrepancies in readings (museum's assertions that they were overcharged for gas services and being taxed when they had tax exempt status); includes a financial statement of bills rendered to the N-YHS between July 1931 and March 1932 which summarizes readings, electric demand, and charges; correspondence with The New York Genealogical and Biographical Society in regard to genealogical reference requests, letters of introductions for visiting researchers, and requests for genealogical publications for the Society's library. Subject: Hatfield Family.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New York Public Library (Box 159, Folder 8)
    Exchanges between the N-YHS Librarian A.J.Wall and various staff members of the New York Public Library in regard to galley proofs of Manhattan maps sent to the Society; setting up of the bindery at the N-YHS; photostat requests. Subjects: Wilberforce Eames, Moore Family, Dictionary of American Biography, Jacob Bailey Moore.
  - Correspondence 1930-1932. New York State (Box 159, Folder 9)